Hello and welcome back to part two of
this video where we are going to be doing
our second parter where we are going
to be looking at gas law stoichiometry
using the ideal gas law specifically.
So we're going to be balancing chemical
equations and going through the step
by step process of how to read word
problems, digest them, and break them
down in these different problems.
So in part one, we focus
on STP related problems.
So these are going to be
a little bit trickier.
We'll be going through how to
essentially balance problems.
So going through tips and tricks
behind that, how to read word
problems and to digest them in
your introductory chemistry course.
And we're going to be looking at exactly
how do you identify when to use the ideal
gas law, when to use partial pressures,
and how to go through even limiting
reagent problems focusing on gas laws.
So this is a very comprehensive
guide on how to solve these.
Thank you so much for stopping by.
If it's your first time here,
hit that like button and comment
below if you have questions.
So let's go dive into these
and let's try to figure out
all about this type of problem.
But when it comes to the ideal gas
law, this is always referring to
what the current condition is of the
gas after the reaction occurred, or
even before the reaction occurred.
So what is the condition?
Now, the big thing about this is you
have four different variables, which are
pressure, volume, temperature, and moles.
You need three out of four of
these to be able to use this
formula, or it can get a little bit
tricky and a little complicated.
So generally you're always
given three out of the four.
So when we are looking at these, we are
going to be exploring all the different
formulas in many different problems.
So let's take a look at how to use
these, use these starting with STP.
Alright, so our first problem in part
two is we are going to be looking
at the stoichiometry of the same
problem we ended with in part one.
So which is, was evolving the
oxidation of glucose within our body.
So one thing about it that we learned
last time is that glucose is broken
down and as a result we breathe out CO2.
So this is one of the most
common reactions that we see.
Let's take a look at this problem
and how we are going to digest it.
Alright, so stoichiometry
with the ideal gas law.
So if I take the same chemical
equation like I had before and
I ask you this time to calculate
the volume of carbon dioxide gas.
Produced when you have 24.
5 grams of glucose and it's
consumed at body temperature,
so 37 degrees Celsius and at 0.
970 atmospheres.
So let's go through the problem.
How would we do it?
What would we start with?
Well, the first thing you always want
to check is do you have a balanced
chemical equation, which we do, right?
It's the same one from before.
The next thing is you want to
look through your, look through
your problem and kind of identify
all the key bits of information.
Right, we have essentially how
much glucose we have, we have
our temperature, and then we
also have what our pressure is.
But we're asked to figure out the
volume, so you have to reorganize
the ideal gas law and get all the
different pieces that are required.
So let's kind of go through and see,
do we have all the correct units here?
Well, the first one that I
can kind of spot out at the
bottom here is that pressure.
As in atmospheres, which one way to
always check yourself is doesn't match the
units of your ideal gas constant, right?
So you can see it's liters,
moles, atmosphere, Kelvin.
So we have atmospheres.
We got one down.
Let's look at temperature, right?
Temperature is at 37 degrees
Celsius up here at the top.
So does that match your temperature here?
And you can see that it doesn't.
So we need to now convert
temperature to Kelvin.
So what we'll do is we'll
take 37 degrees C add to 73.
15.
And what you're going to get is 310.
15 Kelvin is your temperature.
So now that one's good.
Alright, now what about moles?
Well, moles is what we can actually
get with our, our glucose, right?
So we have 24.
5 grams of glucose in the problem.
So, being that, we need to convert
that to moles of CO2, right?
Which is our gas.
That's the thing that most people
mess up when they do this problem
for the first time is they try
to just get the moles, right?
Which is great, but you need to make
sure that it is your moles of your gas.
That's really important It has to be moles
of your gas So if we were to do the same
step as before right from their previous
problem We'll divide this by the molar
mass, which was a hundred and eighty
point fifteen grams of glucose and And
that's equivalent to one mole of glucose.
And now what we're going to
now do is get it to moles using
our chemical equation, right?
And it's for every one mole of glucose
is equivalent to six moles of CO2, right?
So one to six ratio.
Let's write that down, right?
One mole glucose and that's
equivalent to six moles of CO2, right?
So six moles CO2.
All right, now we want to check
that all your R units cancel, right?
So we see grams of glucose
cancels grams of glucose, right?
And then we can also see moles
of glucose cancels moles.
So we're in the right unit.
So that means we have our last
piece once we calculate this.
So when we put all this into
our calculator, you'll take 24.
5, divide it by 180.
15, times that by 6, and
what you should get is 0.
8159595 moles.
And keep in mind, you generally
don't want to round this until
the very end of your problem.
It's usually very standard
practice for most, um, chemistry
problems is round at the end.
So now we have our moles, which
was our last piece of the puzzle.
So what we're now going to do is take
our ideal gas law and plug everything in.
So let's do it.
So what do we have?
Well, we have our first
number, which is our moles.
So let's take that.
So we're going to copy that
number and paste that down here.
And let's kind of change our
color to kind of match here.
So we got blue and blue.
Now we'll take our r
constant, which is in red.
So that is 0.
08206.
You can see that at
the top of your screen.
And then we're going to times that
by the temperature, which was 310.
15, and I apologize for not putting units
into this, but it's also to save space.
And then we're going to
divide all that by 0.
970 atmospheres.
Okay, so that's going to be on bottom,
and then we're going to divide everything.
All right, so when we put all that
into our calculator, we'll take 0.
8159595 times that by 0.
08206 times by 310.
15, it equals, then divide by 0.
970, and what you're going to get is 21.
4 liters as your final volume
for this number, right?
So that is our answer.
and how we do these harder problems.
Okay, let's take a look at the next one.
Sometimes with stoichiometry and the
ideal gas law, you will also have to use
Dalton's law, which is the law of partial
pressure, meaning that if you add the
pressure of each individual gas together
that's in the container, The total
pressure will be all of them added up.
So, let's say if I were to do this
experiment, which all of my students have
done, all the students at my school do
in terms of the introductory chemistry,
is essentially you take a metal,
you react with HCl, you collect gas.
So, let's say if we want
to look in that farther.
So, hydrogen gas is produced when aluminum
metal reacts with hydrochloric acid.
A sample of aluminum produced 511
milliliters of H2 gas, which is
collected over water at 300 Kelvin
and 745 millimeters of mercury.
Determine the mass of aluminum reacted.
And then we have the partial
pressure of hydro, of, of water
here, so of H2O that is here.
So with all that, all those
pieces of information, what
exactly are we going to do?
Well, I wrote out the steps
to help map out the problem.
The first thing you need to do with this
type of longer stoichiometry problem is we
need to predict and balance the problem.
After that, we want to write
down all the given numbers to see
like, okay, we want to convert
everything to the ideal gas units.
Remember, our goal is the mole,
so then we want to make sure we
get our moles, and then we want
to convert to our final units.
So that's a lot of steps to remember.
So let's break this problem
down one step at a time.
Okay, so predict imbalance.
So with this one, I essentially
took out the excerpt from what was
important, which was the first line.
And what it says is that hydrogen
gas is produced, okay, when
aluminum metal reacts with HCl.
Now that doesn't mean that it's
every ingredient here, but it
does give you a hint at what
essentially is reacting together.
So that tells you that the product
was H2, which is one of the products.
Now, it also says that you have
aluminum reacting with HCl.
So one thing when you're trying to
predict these is you gotta be able
to recognize what are the different
types of reactions by writing down
what your individual recipes are.
So in this case, we have A plus B,
C, meaning that A is going to kick
out B to do a single replacement
reaction, or single displacement.
So in this case, what
is your displaced part?
Well, that's going to be hydrogen.
And the other thing is aluminum
is going to react with chlorine.
Now whenever we predict a reaction, we
do not bring any subscripts with us.
There weren't any to begin with,
but you need to make sure you write
down your charges because they
need to be swapped dropped, right?
So meaning that the three from
aluminum needs to come down.
and become a subscript for chlorine.
So we're going to take a three and
put it right down here at the side.
Now with that, all the subscripts are
good, but you'll see really quickly is
that this is not a balanced reaction.
So the tip that I have in the
top left corner is we should
even the odds, just like we said
earlier, which where can we start?
Well, one thing you can see is
that I have three chlorines.
On one side, and I have one on the
left, I also have two hydrogens and
one hydrogen on the left as well.
So how exactly can we
try to balance those?
So if I think of evening the
odds, if I put a three on the
left, well then they're both odds.
That doesn't really even it out.
So let's, what's the next
best number to choose?
Well, if I put a, let's say a two
in front of aluminum chloride,
making six, which is now even.
And now I put essentially a six over
here in front of HCl, also even.
And what does that do is, well,
that evens the odds, that evens that
odd subscript, which is crucial.
Now, what can we do from there?
Well, our chlorines are balanced.
What about our hydrogens?
Well, I have six on the left.
How many do I have on the right?
I have two, right, that are right here.
So what can I do there is I can
put a three in front of that.
That's balanced.
And now what about aluminum?
And we can see, oh,
that's not quite balanced.
So let's fix that for ourselves.
So two aluminums, Reacts with 6
HCl to make 2AlCl3 and 3 hydrogens.
So we gotta balance the problem, right?
And you always wanna check
in case you overbalance, like
can you reduce the numbers?
Like can I divide them all by 2 or by 3?
You always wanna check.
In this case, you can't.
Let's take a look at our next step.
Alright, you wanna now write down all the
given values, convert them to the units
that you find in PV is equal to nRT.
So what you need to match
your ideal gas constant.
So let's write everything
down in the problem.
So the first thing that we
have is a sample of aluminum
produced 511 milliliters of gas.
Now if you remember the ideal gas
law constant needs to be in liters.
So what we're first going to
do is convert that to liters.
So 511 milliliters.
is essentially equivalent to a
thousand milliliters is one liter.
So we'll divide by a
thousand and we'll have 0.
55 liters of H, H2 gas.
Okay.
So that's part of it.
We have 300 Kelvin.
So that one's okay.
So we can write that down as well.
And we also have 745 millimeters
of mercury in the problem too.
So, do we want to use that pressure
though, because that's telling
you what the total pressure is.
It's not referring to the
gas we're interested in or
what we have information on.
All the information that we have
in this problem, for the most
part, is referring to, especially
the volume of the gas, is H2 gas.
So if that is H2, what we need to do
is essentially find the pressure of H2.
So let's take our
partial pressure up here.
So take our formula down and what
we are going to do is rearrange it
to solve for the pressure of H two.
So if I were to do that
right, we can see that.
Well, if the pressure of H two is on
one side, essentially what we need
to do is subtract the pressure of
water to get the pressure of H two.
So we gotta rearrange our equation, right?
And I'll put the original one back
up here just so you can see, right?
We subtracted the water from
both sides is what happened.
Now, we were given the partial pressure
of water, which was at 24 mmHg, so
what we'll do is, is take the 745 mmHg.
Then we'll subtract 24 millimeters
of mercury, and what we're going to
do is convert this to atmospheres.
So this entire number here,
we're going to divide by 760.
So when you get your 740, or
sorry, 721 millimeters of mercury,
you'll divide that by 760.
Now when we have that, what we are going
to essentially get in the end is 0.
948684 atmospheres.
which is going to be your pressure.
Okay, so we have our, we have our, um,
our liters, we have our temperature,
and then we have our atmospheres.
We have three out of the four conditions
required to use the ideal gas law.
So now with that, that's what we're
going to do next, is for our last step
is we're going to plug all these into
the ideal gas law to solve for moles.
Because remember, our goal is the mole.
So if we were to do that,
let's take our numbers.
So we have our n value, Right,
so we'll copy that down.
Uh, sorry, and our n value, our
pressure value, and that's going
to be multiplied by, in this case,
by the volume, which was that 0.
511.
Let's try to color code these.
So we have 0.
511, we'll make that pink to match, 0.
511 liters, and that's going to
all be divided by r, right, which
we have right here on the side.
So that's 0.
08206.
And then that's going to be multiplied
by the temperature, which was 300 Kelvin.
So let's take that
value and bring it down.
Now we're going to plug all
that into our calculator.
So you're gonna take 0.9 4 6 8 6
8 4 times that by 0.511 liters.
And then you're gonna
divide that by 0.08206.
Uh, aim aims at by 300 and what you
will get is 0.0196, or sorry, 1 9 6 9 2.
moles of hydrogen in this problem, right?
Are we done?
And the thing is the last part
was all about, well, can you
convert this to aluminum, right?
What is the mass of
aluminum in this problem?
So here we have the moles of hydrogen.
So now we got to do our last step,
which is using the balanced chemical
equation that we started with.
This is a very, very long and
tough problem when we have to
go through all these steps.
So with that, right,
we are going to take 0.
019692 moles.
And we are going to essentially
convert that to our moles of aluminum.
So using the chemical equation, so we
have moles of H two, and we can use
the chemical equation to see that.
Okay, for every three moles of H
two, we'll write that down here, and
that's equivalent to every two moles.
of aluminum on the left hand side.
Okay, so it's a 3 to 2.
Now when we see, now when we do that,
we can see that moles of H2 cancels
moles of H2, but we want it in mass.
So how do you go from moles to mass?
Is we have to use the molar
mass to do that, which we
have from our periodic table.
So with that being said, we'll take
that one mole of aluminum from the
periodic table, is equivalent to 26.
98 grams of aluminum.
All right, so now that we did
that, we will take our calculator,
we'll take our mole value, times
that by 2, times that by 26.
98, and divide it by 3, and
what you are going to get is 0.
354 grams of aluminum,
which is your final answer.
Because you started with three
significant figures, we have to round
it to three significant figures.
And that's how you do the entire process.
So with stoichiometry, this is,
this can be as tough as it gets.
Really the only thing that can
really go even farther than this
is if you do a limiting reagent
problem, which is our last problem.
So let's take a look.
Limiting reactant stoichiometry can
be some of the toughest problems that
we can ever see in stoichiometry.
Now how do you identify them?
Let's take a look.
So with this one, it says how
many liters of HCl are produced
from 25 grams of BaCl2 And 0.
250 liters of 0.
1 molar H2SO4 at 1
atmosphere and 300 Kelvin.
So we're mixing a liquid
with a solid to make a gas.
Ooh, this is combining
everything together.
So, the way that you can tell that it
is a lemming reagent problem is when
you essentially have two starting
ingredients in a list that are amounts.
So here we have 25 grams, and you also
see that you have the entire concentration
of the solution with its volume, which
is really important to keep in mind.
If the volume is not there,
you probably are fine, but it
needs to have both components.
So now the other part about it is
it doesn't mention, that doesn't
give us the formula either.
So we have our, we have to
first start with just balancing.
So we have barium chloride and
sulfuric acid mixing together.
So when we do this, we got
to first remember inside out.
So we will do the inside and
the outside will bond together.
So now, as I said before, you
don't bring the subscripts.
So we'll take just H plus.
and Cl minus.
Notice how they're already balanced,
so you don't need to swap drop.
And then you have barium 2
plus, and then sulfate 2 minus.
We bring the ions.
All right, now you see that they're both
twos, so that means they're the same
charge, so they cancel each other out.
We are good and balanced
in terms of charges.
Now, is the chemical equation balanced?
Let's take a look.
Well, this is where I say start
with the polyatomics and do what
I refer to as the zigzag method.
Meaning, uh, when I look, uh, here, we
see we have sulfate on the left and right.
We have one on the left, one on the right.
So now let's take a
look at ZIG over to H2.
We have two on the left, and now
we're gonna look in ZAG to the other
H, and we see that we have one.
They are not balanced.
So let's put a two here.
Now they are.
So as a result, I'll now look at
chlorine, and we can see that,
hey, chlorine is now balanced.
We have two and two.
And if you look at the barium, you
can see that's balanced as well.
Everything balanced when
you zigzag back and forth.
Now that we have that,
let's go to our next step.
So from this part of the problem,
remember our goal is the mole, so we had
these different starting ingredients.
We had 25 grams of barium chloride, And 0.
25 liters of 0.
1 molar H2SO4.
So what's the first thing
you should start with?
Well, let's start with the
barium chloride, being that
that's by itself over here.
So if I were to take that number
and I were to just drag it down, how
can we convert it to moles, right?
That is our entire idea here, is we
want to get it to moles of HCl because
that's the gas we're interested in.
So what we need to do is to convert
grams to moles, is use the molar mass.
So we have 208.
23 grams of Bacl2, and that's
equivalent to one mole of Bacl2.
And now we're going to use our chemical
formula, which is one mole of Bacl2
is equivalent to two moles of HCl.
All right, so now that we have that
in moles, we're going to stop there.
I'm going to show you a way to make
these problems 10 times faster,
as we just want to get two moles.
Um, so now our grams cancel.
Great.
Now, when we are to solve this,
what we are going to end up getting
is we'll see that we have 0.
240 moles of HCl that is possibly made
if all the barium chloride is used.
So let's now go do the other part.
Well, now with this one, it's always
tricky to do solution stoichiometry.
always start with the volume
because it's a term by itself.
So when we do that, we can
actually cancel it using molarity
as a conversion term, right?
Molarity is moles over liters.
So meaning that we have 0.
1 mole and that's equivalent
to one liter of H2SO4.
Okay, so we'll put one liter and as you
can notice is that, Ooh, liters cancels.
Great.
And now, once again, we'll use the
chemical formula which told us one mole of
H2SO4 was equivalent to two moles of HCl.
So let's add that here.
We'll have essentially one mole H2SO4 on
the bottom, two moles of HCl on the top.
Okay, and then once again.
you'll see units cancel,
which is what we want.
All right, so now when we
do the math, we'll do 0.
25 times 0.
1 times 2, and what we will get is 0.
0500 moles of HCl.
Now, what we are now going to do is
we've got to compare the two numbers,
the one that we have all the way in
the top left, Right of the screen,
and then the one that we have all
the way on the bottom of the screen.
The one in purple and green.
So if you compare them, which one is
smaller, and the thing is you're gonna
see the one next to me is a lot smaller.
That means that this
ingredient ran out completely.
Didn't react as much as the other one did.
So this is your limiting
reagent in this case, right?
So we want to put a A big L, a big
LR here to tell us, Hey, this is our
limiting reagent, which means H two.
So four ran out.
So this is the calculation
you want to finish and or use
in terms of the last step.
So we're gonna use this to figure out
what our vol, our final volume is.
All right, so now we
have our ideal gas law.
We listed all of our values out,
so we want to use our limiting
reagent mole value, which was 0.05.
We will use our ideal gas law constant,
right, which we plugged in as well.
We have our temperature value as well,
which we'll use too, which is 300 Kelvin.
And then it's all going to be divided by
our pressure, which was one atmosphere.
Now, when you put all this into your
calculator, you're going to take 0.
05 times that by 0.
08206 times that by 300.
And you will have a volume of 1.
23 liters, okay?
So you do not have to use the Ideal
Gas Law twice, is what this is trying
to tell you by cutting this shorter.
You just have to see which
one has less moles, right?
And that you can do that for
any limiting reagent problem.
You can even do it for mass stoichiometry
too, or solution stoichiometry.
It saves you a little bit of time.
That wraps up the end of part
two of this video series.
I hope that this helped you understand a
little bit better gas law stoichiometry.
As you saw that it can get a
little bit complex, but with more
practice, you can master this.
So if you need any help, please
reach out to me, talk to me.
Uh, if you see me on campus, come say hi.
Um, if you are someone just viewing
this video, please feel free to
comment below and ask questions.
I'm always checking this to reach
out to help students just like you.
Uh, and if this is your first time
here, please hit the like button
and subscribe to the channel for
more introductory chemistry, organic
chemistry, and biochemistry content.
Alright y'all, I hope y'all have a
wonderful day and I'll see y'all later.
Bye now!